マスター コーヒーをもう一杯
あの 実は 私
私 折木さんに
頼みがあるんです
頼み
はい
本当なら これは私だけの問題ですから
お願いできる筋合いではありません
だから まず話を聞いてくれませんか
まあ 聞くだけなら
はい
退屈な窓辺に吹き込む風に
顔を顰めたのは照れくさ　その裏返し
KamiGami
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
曖昧に頷く掌の今日
描いてる自分は少し大袈裟で
何かが変わりそうな気がしているよ
I'll have another coffee, please.
心に呼びかける君のせいだね
Um...
曇り空覗いた予感
Actually, I...
手を伸ばそう　いつよりも力強い勇気で
I have a request!
光も影もまだ遠くで
A request?
それでも僕らは優しさの理由が知りたい
Yes.
To be honest, this is something I should solve on my own,
so I have no right to ask you for help...
今は誰の名前でもない
But please, just hear me out first!
輝きの彼方へ
全部過去になる前に見つけに行こう
If that's all I need to do, yeah.
Hyouka
Thank you!
Inheritors of the Classics Club and Its Circumstances
另有隐情的古籍研究社之后裔
It's about my uncle. His name was Sekitani Jun.
私には 関谷純という叔父がいたのですが
Please help me remember what he told me!
私がその叔父から何を聞いたのか
思い出させてほしいんです
I don't really get it.
よく分からんのだが
Oh, sorry. I skipped a few details.
すみません 先走りすぎました
ちゃんと順を追ってお話します
I'll explain things from the start.
実はその叔父は 七年前にインドに行ったっきり
My uncle went to India seven years ago, and nobody has heard from him since then.
行方不明になっています
Japanese man missing
Japanese man goes missing
子供頃の私は その叔父によく懐いていました
When I was little, I was very attached to him.
どんな突拍子もない質問にも必ず答えてくれて
He would answer any question I asked, no matter how crazy it was.
It was as if there was nothing he didn't know about.
知らないことなど何もないような人でした
私が幼稚園の頃 叔父が古典部だったことを知り
When I was in kindergarten, I heard that he was in the Classics Club,
それに興味を持ちました
and I became interested in it as well.
I think it's because "Classics" sounded similar to the "candy sticks" I loved at home.
いつも家にあった 酢昆布に語呂が似ていたからだと思います
That's a really bad pun.
駄洒落か
One day, I asked him about the Classics Club.
ある日私は古典部に纏わる何かについて叔父に訪ねました
That was the one and only question he avoided answering.
するとその時だけ なぜか妙に返事を嫌がったんです
He avoided it?
嫌がった
Yes. I threw a huge tantrum, and eventually he relented.
はい
私がずいぶん駄々をこねて
ようやく叔父は答えてくれたんですが
When I heard his answer, I...
その答えを聞いた私は
You what?
お前は
泣きました
I cried.
恐ろしかったのか 悲しかったのか
I don't know if it was because it was scary or because it was depressing, but I cried my eyes out.
大泣きしました
You cried...
泣いた
What's more, I remember my mother came running in surprise,
しかも母が驚いて飛んできてくれたんですが
but my uncle didn't even try to calm me down.
叔父はそんな私をあやしたりはしてくれなかったんです
その時のことは
It was such a big shock that I can't remember anything else.
ただショックが大きかっただけで
これ以上は何も覚えていません
But back when I entered junior high, I couldn't stop thinking about it.
でも中学生になった頃 気になり出しました
叔父はなぜ答えを渋ったのか
Why did he try to dodge the question?
Why didn't he try to calm me down?
なぜあやしてくれなかったのか
Since then,
それからの私は やれることはやったつもりです
I've done everything I could do.
疎遠になっている関谷家にも
Though we drifted apart from the Sekitanis, I still tried to stay in touch as much as possible.
出来る範囲で接触しました
But no matter what I do, I can't remember what it was!
ですが どうしても思い出せなかったんです
だから 私は神山高校に入った時
So, when I started at Kamiyama High, I felt like the Classics Club was my last hope.
古典部が最後の望みだと思いました
That's the "personal thing" you were talking about?
それが 一身上の都合か
But I didn't know that the Classics Club was on the verge of being disbanded.
ですが 古典部が廃部寸前だったとは知りませんでした
I asked the teachers, but none of them remember
職員室で聞いてみても
what happened 45 years ago, when my uncle attended the school.
叔父が高校生だった四十五年前のことを知っている先生もいなくて
で
So? Why did you come to me?
なぜそこで俺に助けを求める
それは
Well...
Because you can solve mysteries that I can't even fathom!
それは 折木さんが私では想像もしなかった結論を出してくれそうだからです
Like the locked door, the library book,
あの鍵の時とか
本の時
and the secret club!
そして勧誘メモの時もです
I just know that you'll be able to lead me to the truth!
折木さんなら
きっと私を答えまで導いてくれると思うんです
買いかぶられても困る
You really shouldn't overestimate me.
That was just dumb luck.
あんなものはただの運だ
Then let me count on that luck!
なら その運に頼らせてください
I don't want to.
気が進まん
You could say that this mystery
これは
千反田という一人の人間の大げさに言えば人生観にもかかわる問題だ
is at the core of Chitanda Eru's very life.
そんなことに省エネ主義のこの俺がすこしでも責任を負おうとでも
Do you really think a low-energy person like me would want to be responsible?
ご冗談を
You've gotta be kidding me.
So why just me?
なぜ 俺だけなんだ
頼れるやつはほかにもいるだろ
Surely there are other people you could talk to as well.
Many hands make light work, right?
人海戦術を使えばいい
お前の友達にも頼んでみればどうだ
Just ask all your friends to help.
折木さん
Oreki...
私は過去を言いふらして回る趣味はありません
I'm not the kind of person who just goes around revealing her past to everyone.
This isn't...
こんなの 誰にでもする話じゃありません
something I can discuss with just anyone.
Sorry.
すまん
I know I'm really asking a lot of you.
私はずいぶん無茶を言っています
I know I shouldn't be getting you mixed up in my past.
自分の思い出に折木さんまで巻き込んではいけないと分かっています
ただ
But...
You might not be as friendly as my uncle, but you answer my questions too!
叔父よりもずっと愛想は悪いけれど
あなたも答えてくれました
愛想が悪くて悪かったな
Please accept my deepest apologies for being unfriendly.
I think I might've seen something of my uncle in you.
私はそんな折木そんに叔父を重ねていたのかもしれません
高校は三年間ある
High school lasts for three years, right?
その間にゆっくり探せばいい
That's more than enough time to investigate this.
I want to remember my uncle,
私は 叔父が死んでしまう前に 答えを思い出したいのです
before he's dead.
死んでしまう
Before he's dead?
Yes.
はい
If someone goes missing for seven years,
法律では七年の間 生死が不明となれば
they're considered legally dead.
死亡したとして扱うことができるそうです
I see.
そうなのか
My uncle's family wants closure as well.
叔父の家でも いずれこの件に区切りをつける予定です
They're of modest means, but they've planned a funeral.
ささやかですが 葬儀を営むそうです
So...
だから
だから私は叔父が私に伝えてくれたことを胸に
So I wanted to find out what he told me back then...
その葬儀に　望みたくて…
And prepare myself for the funeral, as well.
I'm sorry.
すみません
It's not like you have anything better to do, right?
奉太郎
どうせやりたいことなんかないんでしょ
I can't take on this responsibility for you.
俺はお前に対して 責任を取れない
So I can't say that I'll take on your request.
だから
お前の頼みを引き受けるとは言わない
だが その話を心に留めておいて
But I'll keep all this in mind,
and if I hear anything that might point you in the right direction,
ヒントになるようなことを見かけたら
必ず報告しよう
I'll let you know.
If you have any trouble interpreting the clues,
その解釈に手間取るようなら
I can assist you with that.
その時も手助けする
Okay.
はい
If you can agree to those terms, I'll help you.
それでよければ
手伝わせてもらう
Thank you very much!
ありがとうございます
I'm sure you'll be able to help me!
どうかよろしくお願いします
Yeah.
Though people say high school life is colorful,
高校生活と言えども
it isn't all fun and games.
決してバラ色だけではない
For example, we have exams.
例えば定期試験
At Kamiyama High, midterms have begun.
神山高校でも一学期中間テストが始まった
All club activities are put on hold during the exams,
この試験期間中はすべての部活が休止になる
and needless to say, that includes the Classics Club as well.
それはもちろん古典部もなのだが
普段から何もやっていないので
We didn't do much to begin with, though,
正直ほんとんど変わらない
Library
so not a lot has changed.
We probably could've kept meeting in the clubroom as usual,
ならば 普段どおりにしていてもいいようなものだが
but with no key available we didn't have much choice.
鍵が貸し出されないのでは仕方がなかった
First Semester  Midterm Exam         Schedule
period
Contemp. Lit.     Contemp. Soc.          English I               Math A
Contemp. Lit.     Math I           World History B      Compr. Sci
Classics
First Semester Midterm Examinations
Day Two, Period Two
Mathematics I
First Semester Midterm Examinations
Day Three, Period Two
World History B
First Semester Midterm Examinations
Day Four, Period Two
Comprehensive Science
Okay, pens down!
はい 終了
中間テスト終了 やれやれ
First Semester  Midterm Exam         Schedule
period
Contemp. Lit.     Contemp. Soc.          English I               Math A
Contemp. Lit.     Math I           World History B      Compr. Sci
Classics
Finally, the midterms are over... Jeez.
Greetings.
前略
I am writing to you from Istanbul.
私は今イスタンブールにいます
A few things went wrong when I arrived, so I'm currently stuck in the Japanese consulate and haven't seen much of the city yet.
ちょっと失敗しちゃって 日本常事館に籠っているから
町の中はまだ見てないんだけどね
What did you do this time?
何やったんだ 姉貴
この旅面白いわ
I'm really enjoying this trip!
I'm sure that ten years from now, I'll be able to look back on these days without regret.
きっと十年後
この毎日のことを惜しまない
ところで 古典部はどう
By the way, how's the Classics Club?
Has anyone else joined?
部員は増えた
There's one other thing on my mind, so I thought I'd better mention it.
それで ちょっと気になることがあったから
書いておくね
あんた文集作る気ある
Will you be making an anthology?
The Classics Club used to release an anthology every year at the culture fair.
古典部は毎年文化祭で文集を出してたんだけど
Are you still doing that?
今も続いてるのかな
If so, you might be wondering what you need to do.
続いてるとしたら
もしかして作り方が分かんないかもしれないと思って
The Classics Club's prior anthologies aren't kept in the library.
古典部の文集は図書室にはないからね
You should be able to find them in the clubroom.
探すのは部室
There's this unused medicine safe.
そこに使われてない薬品金庫があって
The back issues are in there.
バックナンバ―はその中
鍵は開いてるわ
It's not locked.
When I arrive in Pristina, I'll give you a call.
じゃ プリスティナに着いたら一度電話するから
かしこ 折木供恵
Greetings, Oreki Tomoe.
A medicine safe?
薬品金庫
You couldn't have chosen a better time to tell me...
タイミング良すぎだろ
小满
物致于此小得盈满
Full Grain
As all things brim with life, the world dresses in green.
Hyouka
Earth Sci. Prep. Room
Really?
本当ですか
本当だ
Yep.
I brought the letter with me, too.
その手紙もここに持ってきた
なるほど
So it's in a medicine safe, is it?
薬品金庫ね
ここにはないぞ
It's not here, though.
That's right! I haven't seen anything like that here!
そう言えば 見当たりませんでした
じ  じゃ 文集は
B-But then what about the anthologies? The anthologies?
文集は
Chill out, Chi.
チーちゃん
落ち着いて 落ち着いて
"Chi"?
チーちゃんって
千反田 その手紙には部室の薬品金庫って書いてあるだけだ
Chitanda, all she said was that the medicine safe is in the clubroom.
姉貴がここを卒業したのは二年前だからな
My sister graduated two years ago.
その間に部室が変わったんだ
The clubroom has changed since then.
なるほど そういうことですか
I see! So that's what happened!
So, do you know which room it was two years ago?
それで 折木
二年前はどこだったか分かってるの
顧問に聞いてきた
I asked our club advisor.
生物準備室だとさ
Apparently, it was the biology prep room.
珍しく準備がいいじゃない
Wow, you really did your homework!
効率を上げただけだ
I just took the most efficient approach.
Such enthusiasm!
張り切ってるわね
そんなことはない
Not even close.
俺は一般に張り切らない
I don't know the meaning of the word "enthusiasm".
じゃ 行きましょう
Then, let's go!
By the way, what about Fukube?
そう言えば 福部さんは
ああ 手芸部よ
That sew-and-sew?
何か夏のフャッションシーンを 先取りーだとかなんとか言ってたけど
He was going on about taking a sneak peek at some summer fashion thing...
Oreki!
折木さん
あれ 開きませんよ
Huh? It's locked.
どなたがいらっしゃいませんか
Is anyone in there?
いやーすまない 鍵を掛けてた
Oh, sorry.
I'd locked the door.
わが壁新聞部に入部希望かな
Are you interested in joining the News Poster Club?
いいえ 違います
Not exactly.
あの ここは壁新聞部の部室なんですか
Is this the News Poster Club's room, then?
そうだけど
Yeah, pretty much.
この匂い
That smell... Cologne?
香水
いや 消臭剤か
Or rather... Air freshener?
So, how can I help you?
で 何か用でも
あの 私 古典部の部長
I'm the president of the Classics Club, Chitanda Eru.
千反田えると申します
三年E組の遠垣内先輩ですよね
You're Tougaito from Class 3-E, right?
How do you know my name?
どうして俺の名前を
I remember seeing you last year at the Manninbashis'.
去年 万人橋さんのお宅でお姿を見掛けていたものですから
万人橋の家で
At the Manninbashis'?
待てよ もしかして神田の千反田さん
Wait a moment, would you happen to be one of the Chitandas from Kanda?
はい
Yes. You've been a great help to my father.
父がお世話になっています
Ah, please, the feeling's mutual...
いや こちらこそ
I see, a Chitanda.
そうか 千半田の
何を気にしているんだ？
Why's he so tense?
それで 何か？
So, how can I help you?
はい 実はこの生物準備室に
Right! We heard the Classics Club's old anthologies were being kept here in the biology prep room.
古典部の文集のバックナンバーが保管されていると聞いて来たんです
Biology Prep. Room
ここは以前古典部の部室だったそうですね
This used to be the Classics Club's room, right?
Oh... Oh, right. I think it was when I was a first-year student, yeah.
俺が一年の頃はそうだったかな
So...
では ではその文集はご存知ですか
So would you happen to know anything about the anthologies?
いや ないね
No... No.
そうですか ありがとうございました
I see. Thank you very much.
帰るな
Hold on!
Sorry, but they have to be in here somewhere!
あの すみません ここにあるはずなんです
Please, let us look for them!
探させてください
悪いけど 先ないって言ったはずだよ
Sorry, but like I just said, they're not here.
But...
そんな
さ 帰ろうか
Well, let's be off.
ちょ
Wait!
あんたおかしいと思わないの？
Don't you think it's weird?
思う
I do.
だったら帰るな！
Then stick around!
ま 気の毒だけど 他をあたってくれ
I'm sorry, but you'll have to look somewhere else.
But we heard that they were here!
でも ここにあるっていう手がかりを見つけたんです
ここになければ 学校中を探さなければならなくなるんです
If we can't find them here, we'll have to search the entire school!
学校中
The entire school? That's out of the question.
冗談じゃない
少しの時間でいいんです 中を見せてください
Please let us in!
Just for a minute!
俺からも
Please.
あまり部外者に入ってほしくないんだよ
I'd prefer not to let outsiders in.
No offense, but this is a classroom first and a clubroom second!
先輩 でもここは部室である前に教室ですよね
君は？
And you are?
古典部の伊原摩耶花です
Ibara Mayaka from the Classics Club.
わかった
Very well.
いいよ 探せばいい
You can take a look inside.
ただ あまり引っ掻き回さないでくれよ
Just don't make a mess.
One day, one article!
他の部員さんは？
Where are the other club members?
They're on break today.
ああ 今日は休みなんだ
I was just thinking about what to put in the June issue.
俺は六月号のネタを考えてた
「神高月報」っていうんだが
It's called the Kami High Monthly.
It has quite a history. We're nearing the 500th issue, in fact.
歴史も古くて もう五百号近い
この部室にはないみたいね
Looks like it's not here either.
やっぱりそうですか
I see. That's too bad...
What should we do,
どうする？ 折木？
Oreki?
先輩
Tougaito,
部室の入れ替えの時に何か荷物の出し入れはありませでしたか
did anything get moved around when you switched clubrooms?
そういえば ダンボール箱をいくつか運んだな
Now that you mention it, we had to carry a few cardboard boxes.
ダンボール箱ですね
Cardboard boxes?
ああ
Yeah.
となると
Which means...
だがそいつを手に入れるのはちょっと難題だ
The tricky part would be getting to it, though.
ここはカマをかけてみるか
Let's give this guy a good shake and see what falls out.
We're sorry, but there's so much stuff in this room
すみません
どうもこの部屋は物が多くて 探し物には手間がかかりそうです
that it'd take ages for us to look through it all.
I'd like to ask our club advisor
顧問の先生にも手伝ってもらって
to help us give it a more thorough search.
徹底的に捜索したいんですが
Is that okay?
いいですかね
それはだめだ
No.
あまり引っ掻き回さないでくれと言っただろ
I told you not to make a mess.
But this is the only lead we have!
でも ここになかったら もう手がかりがないんです
責任もって全部元通りにしますから お願いします
We'll take full responsibility for returning everything to the way it—
だめだと言っている！
I said no!
そんな
But...
俺は忙しいんだ
I'm busy!
I don't care about your thorough search!
何が徹底的に捜索だ
Your anthologies aren't here!
ここにはお前らの文集などないんだ
わかったら帰れ！
You got that? Get outta here!
ビンゴだ
Bingo.
先輩 俺たちは薬品金庫の中身に興味があるんですよ
We're after what's in the medicine safe.
何だと！
What?!
その中に文集があるはずなんです
The anthologies are supposedly in there.
それさえあれば 先輩の手を煩わせることもないんですね
That's all we need. No skin off your back, right?
Either way, we have things we need to do in the library right now,
ところで 俺たちこれから図書室に用があるんですが
俺たちが行ったあとで もし文集が見つかったら
so if you should happen to find the anthologies after we've left,
we'd be grateful if you could bring them to the earth science prep room.
地学準備室に置いておいてくれませんか
It isn't locked.
鍵は開いています
Y-You...
お前
お前は俺を
What do you think you're...
What do I think?
先輩を？
Very well.
わかった 見つかったらそうしておくよ
If I find them, I'll bring them to you.
お願いします
Thank you very much.
さあ 行こうか
Let's go.
おい 一年
Hey, first-year.
お前の名前だけ聞いてなかったな
You haven't introduced yourself yet.
折木奉太郎
Oreki Houtarou.
I apologize.
悪いとは思ってますよ
ねえ 折木
Hey, Oreki.
どうしてこんなところで待ってるのよ
Why are we waiting here?
省エネだ
To save energy.
Oh, come on.
何よそれ
By the way, Chitanda.
ところで 千半田
What is Tougaito's family famous for?
遠垣内の家はどういう方面で有名なんだ？
そうですね
Well...
They're quite well-known in the field of junior high school education.
中等教育に影響力があって
教育関係者が何人もいるお家柄ですね
Many people from their family work in education, in fact.
なるほどな
I see.
五分経過
It's been five minutes.
そろそろ戻るか
Shall we head back?
Earth Sci. Prep. Room
Look what we have here.
お 来てるな
Hyouka
No 28
Kami
yama
High
School
Classics
Club
It's the anthologies!
文集だわ
Hey, Oreki, what just happened?
ちょっと折木
あんたこれどうやったの？
何かしてたの？
Did you do something?
Just a bit of blackmail.
まあ ちょっと脅迫をな
脅迫？
Blackmail?
ああ
Ibara,
Is targeted!
伊原
お前口は堅い方か
can you keep a secret?
何よ
Huh?
If you tell me not to talk about it, I won't.
言うなと言われればしゃべらないわよ
そうか
I see.
Then, let's start from the beginning.
じゃあ まず始め
遠垣内が部屋から出てきたとき
When Tougaito came out of that room, he was clearly wary of us.
やつは明らかに俺たちを警戒していた
確かに
That's true.
How about inside the room?
室内の様子はどうだ？
窓を開けて扇風機を回していたが
The windows were open and he had the fan turned on,
but from that position the papers on the desk were almost blown away.
あの位置ではテーブルの上の用紙も吹き飛ばしてしまいかねん
空気の入れ替えをしたかったんでしょ
He wanted to air out the room.
そうだ
Exactly.
では なぜ換気をしたかったのか
But why did he want to air out the room?
Or rather,
もっといえば なぜ内側から鍵をかけ
why would he lock the door and set up an infrared sen—
赤外センサーまで設置して
ちょ ちょっと待って
Wait a moment!
What are you talking about? What infrared sensor?
何よその赤外センサーって
There were these tiny boxes on the corridor walls that I hadn't seen before.
廊下の両側に見慣れない小さな箱があったんだ
And if that gadget with an antenna in the room was the receiver,
それに室内にあったあのアンテナが付いてたのが受信機だとすると
あそこを誰かが通れば アラームが鳴る仕組みなんだろう
then it must have been set up to alert him when someone passed by.
How did you figure that out?
よくそんなのがわかったわね
まあ 状況からの推測だけどな
Just a guess based on the situation.
問題はなぜそこまで警戒して
But why would he take so much care to start airing out the room
接近者が来るや 慌てて部屋の換気をしたのか
as soon as someone passed by?
To clear out a smell?
においを消すため？
それが妥当だろう
Most likely.
He also smelled of air freshener.
やつは消臭スプレーのにおいもさせていた
What smell would he want to cover up that badly?
で そこまでして人に知られたくないにおいとなると
Tobacco, right?
タバコね
教育界の名家の御曹司ともなれば
The heir of a family famous in the field of education
何としてでも
couldn't allow anyone to find him smoking illegally.
不法行為を見つかるわけにはいかないってことだな
なるほどね
I see.
まあ もし千半田が風邪を引いていなかったら
Though, if Chitanda didn't have a cold, she would've smelled it right away.
一発でにおいに気付いてただろうがな
But wait,
でも 待って
結局文集ってどこにあったの？
where were the anthologies, then?
薬品金庫の中だろ
In the medicine safe, of course.
お れ き
O-re-ki!
I-I'm not making fun of you.
べ 別にからかってるんじゃないぞ
The medicine safe was under that home-made table.
薬品金庫はあの簡易テーブルの下にあったんだ
そして その中にタバコやライターも隠していたんだろう
I guess he must've been hiding his smokes and lighter in there too.
だから 俺が先生と一緒に探させてくれと頼んだとき
That's why he panicked when I suggested
getting a teacher involved in the search.
遠垣内はあんなに慌てたんだ
やっぱり あんた変
You're really weird.
何を
Come on,
典型的な一般人をつかまえて
I'm as average as they come.
みんなー
Hey guys!
ひまわりいいい～
I'm a sunflower!
里志 文集のバックナンバーが見つかったぞ
Satoshi,
we found the old anthologies.
あ 本当だ
Whoa, really?
へえ こんなのだったんだ
So that's how they look!
This one's forty years old, so does that mean it was written by hand?
四十年も前となると さすがに手作りなんだよね
どうした？ 千半田
What's wrong, Chitanda?
Nah, they probably printed it with a mimeograph.
それはガリ版印刷だね 正確には謄写版印刷って言って
Or in other words, a cyclostyle. It was invented in the late 19th century..
明治時代に発明されたものなんだよ
どうした？
What's wrong?
I doubt the school would have had a photocopier during the 1970s.
1970年代だと まだ学校にもコピー機はなかったんだから
折木さん
Oreki...
ほら
Look, this one was photocopied...
こっちはコピー機を使ってる
Come here...
I see...
This is it.
これです
氷菓
"Hyouka".
Issue number two.
第二号
This is what I found back then.
あのとき 私はこれを見つけたんです
I brought it to my uncle
伯父のところにこれを持っていって
and asked him what it was.
これは何かと聞いたんです
思い出したのか
You remembered?
この中を見てください
Please read it.
Hyouka
There is something in here that has to do with my uncle.
これには伯父の事が載っています
何かがあったんです
Something happened 45 years ago in the Classics Club.
四十五年前に この古典部で
"And so, this year the culture fair has come once again.
今年もまた文化祭がやってきた
関谷先輩が去ってからもう一年になる
One year has passed since Sekitani left us.
The year that he began as a hero and finished as a legend.
この一年で 先輩は英雄から伝説になった
The battles he fought, the sacrifices he made,
争いも犠牲も 先輩のあの微笑みさえも
and the smiles he shared
will all be carried along by the river of time, into the distant past.
すべては時の彼方に流されていく
But that is how it should be.
いや その方がいい
憶えていてはならない
It is not something meant to be remembered.
なぜならあれは 英雄譚などではけっしてなかったのだから
It was nothing even close to an epic.
すべては主観性を失って
And as it loses all subjectivity,
it all becomes part of the classics, as per the rules of historic perspective.
歴史的遠近法の彼方で古典になていく
One day we too will just be classic literature on someone's shelf.
いつの日か 現在の私たちも未来の誰かの古典になるのだろう
October 13, 1964. Kooriyama Youko."
1968年10月13日
郡山養子
The year before that was 45 years ago.
ここにある「去年」は四十五年前になります
Which means that the Sekitani mentioned there was my uncle.
ならば 古典部の関谷先輩とは伯父の事でしょう
Sekitani
Whatever it was that he told me, it was related to the Classics Club as well.
その伯父が私に教えてくれた答えも古典部に関することでした
Then it's all right now, I guess?
なら もう大丈夫だろう
But I can't remember what it was!
でも 思い出せないんです
It's...
もうちょっと もうちょっとなのに
It's so close!
What did he tell me that day?
あの日 伯父は何を語ってくれたのでしょう
What happened to my uncle 45 years ago?
四十五年前 伯父に一体何があったと？
調べてみればいいさ
Then why don't you investigate it?
でも 憶えていてはならないって書いてあります
It says right there that it shouldn't be remembered!
もし調べたら 不幸なことになるかもしれません
What if I find out something I never wanted to know?
There are things in the world best left forgotten, right?
忘れられた方がいい事実というものは存在するでしょ？
Even things from 45 years ago?
四十五年も前のことでもか？
違うんですか
Does that matter?
It does.
違うさ
As it says here:
ここに書いてあるじゃないか
"It all becomes part of the classics, as per the rules of historic perspective."
すべては歴史的遠近法の彼方で古典になっていく
It's already in the past..
時効ってことさ
はい
それに 調べるって言ったって
If you want to look into it further, this article refers to the previous year.
第二号に去年のことって書いてあるんだから
創刊号を見ればいいだけの話だ
So why not just check the first issue—
Hey, what's going on?!
ちょっと 何よこれ
The first issue is the only one that's missing!
創刊号だけ欠けてるじゃない
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
Find me, I beg you
まどろみの約束
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
芽生えてた温もり　暖かくて戸惑う
This sprouting warmth confuses us
こんな気持ちをまだ　あなたは分からないよ
Don't you understand this feeling yet?
そんな視線には意味なんて　別にないはず
Normally such random glances hold no meaning
だって友達にしてるのと同じ
Isn't it the same when making friends?
明け方に消えてく　小さな願星
The little shooting stars we wish upon, vanishing into the dawn
夜の間だけの魔法を…
are a magic that only unfolds in the night
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
Find me, I beg you
まどろみの約束
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
次回 栄光ある古典部の昔日
Next time:
Past Days of the Classics Club and Its Glory.
Past Days of the Classics Club and Its Glory